In my family, there's a boy named
trong gia đình nhà con có một cháu
Nguyen Van Son, he's very smart and well-behaved.
Nguyễn Văn Sơn cháu học rất giỏi mà cháu
He went to school and even tutored
ngoan Cháu đi học cháu còn làm gia sư
for half a year before going to university. After half a
đến nửa năm đại học được học được nửa
year of studying, he dropped out of school and wandered around. When he
năm là cháu bị Cháu bỏ học cháu không
came home, for 10 days,
học cho đi lang thang về nhà thì 10 ngày
my family was in a state of
thì gia đình tôi là trong một cái tình
chaos. My father and I fought all
trạng mà bố con đánh nhau cả mười luôn
night, he couldn't sleep, he stayed awake all night. My
đêm nó không ngủ mày nó suốt đêm nó thức
mother stayed awake, my son stayed awake, muttering to himself, his eyes
Mẹ thức con thức mồm Cứ lẩm bẩm mà mắt
staring at people and then laughing. At that time, we
cứ nhìn người ta xong là cười Lúc đấy
didn't know about Buddhism, so we went to
không biết về Phật pháp cho nên là về đi
see fortune tellers everywhere, but he did
xem bói hết mọi nơi trong khi đó cháu
n't change at all for ten years. We
không chuyển một tí nào ròng rã chục năm
invited the monks from Ba Vang Pagoda to
ấy cô ạ Thỉnh được Chư tăng chùa Ba Vàng
help our family. Now everything is peaceful. My mother-in-law
về coi như gia đình Bây giờ là êm ấm mẹ
listens to the Dharma all day. Son and
chồng thì ngồi nghe pháp suốt ngày Sơn
I go to repentance every day. If my
là tôi nào cũng lên sám hối Nếu như mà
family
gia đình mà
hadn't had the opportunity to know about Buddhism, by
chưa biết có duyên biết phật pháp thì
now my mother would probably be dead, and my son would be dead too.
giờ này chắc là mẹ mà chết rồi con chết
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Namo Buddha Shakyamuni. Dieu Tam
Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni Diệu
respectfully greets the head of the group and
Tâm Xin kính chào cô chủ nhiệm cùng toàn
all the esteemed fellow practitioners. Dieu Tam
thể các quý đạo hữu cùng các bạn diệu
is currently the head of the
tâm hiện là đạo tràng trưởng đạo tràng
Truc Son Dharma group in Ninh Binh province, practicing at...  The
Trúc Sơn tỉnh Ninh Bình đang tu tập tại
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, practicing the Six Harmonies at
câu lạc bộ Cúc Vàng tập tu Lục Hòa chùa
Ba Vang Pagoda, respectfully invites
Ba Vàng sau đây diệu tâm xin kính mời
Buddhist follower Nguyen Thi Hang to the
phật tử Nguyễn Thị Hằng lên trên sân
stage to share her story of the
khấu chia sẻ lại câu chuyện Phật Pháp
miraculous power of Buddhism through practice. Dear fellow
Nhiệm Mầu nhờ sự tu tập Phật pháp
practitioners, I am Nguyen Thi
Kính thưa các đạo hữu Con là Nguyễn Thị
Hang, Dharma name Tinh Lieu Tue. Today I
Hằng pháp danh Tịnh Liễu Tuệ Hôm nay con
have come to Ba Vang Pagoda to serve as a soldier. I
được về chùa Ba Vàng Làm Quân
don't know what my life will be like now, but
không biết đến giờ này đến giờ này còn
I am deeply moved. My
như thế nào mà bây giờ con cảm động
family
trong gia đình nhà con
has found refuge in the
con được nương tựa
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, and I
câu lạc bộ Cúc Vàng Và Con Nương Tựa tam
also rely
bảo còn nương tựa
on the Three Jewels, my teacher, and the great monks of Ba Vang Pagoda.
trên sư phụ và đại Chư tăng chùa Ba Vàng
In my family, I have a nephew,
trong gia đình nhà con có một cháu
Nguyen Van Son, who is very intelligent and well-behaved.
Nguyễn Văn Sơn cháu học rất giỏi mà
He went to school and also tutored until
Cháu đi học cháu còn làm gia sư đến khi
he passed the University of Transport entrance exam with
cháu thi đỗ đại học Giao thông vận tải
3 extra points. My family was
tốt đỗ được thừa được 3 điểm gia đình
so happy that we threw a feast for him,
mừng quá với cho cháu liên hoan cho cháu
inviting relatives to eat.
10 mâm cỗ để mời anh em đến ăn cỗ đến
When we enrolled him in university, he
khi gia đình cho cháu lên học thì cháu
studied normally. He continued tutoring
học bình thường Cháu vẫn đi dạy gia sư
until half a year into university,
đến nửa năm đại học được học được nửa
but then he dropped out. He stopped studying and
năm là cháu bị Cháu bỏ học cháu không
wandered around aimlessly.
học cho đi lang thang mặt mũi nho nhem
His character was so filthy and messy, I do
nhuốc nhuốc tâm tính của nó làm sao ấy
n't know what to do.
Thế thì gia đình cũng không biết làm sao
At that time, the family didn't know anything about Buddhism, so they
lúc đấy không biết về Phật pháp cho nên
went to see fortune tellers everywhere and visited various
là về đi xem bói hết mọi nơi cũng đi lễ
places. They followed this path for about
hết mọi chỗ nọ chỗ kia vậy là cứ đi theo
ten years, ma'am. Then, after about ten years, they
dần giã vậy mà chục năm ấy cô ạ tầm chục
met a Four Realms master and a medium.
gặp thầy tứ phủ rồi gặp cô đồng thì đi
They told them that this boy
xem bói họ bảo là nhà chị là thằng này
had a heavy karmic debt to the Four Realms. They said that
là nó bị căn quả nặng rồi tứ phủ Chị
opening a shrine would
phải mở phủ
cost a lot of money, or that it would cost
thì mở phủ thì hết nhiều tiền không thì
hundreds of millions of dong. But they didn't open the shrine, and they just kept humming and humming. Then they said, "
họ bảo là mở phủ thì cũng vài trăm triệu
Just let him go. He'll serve his
ngân nga thì họ bảo là thôi chị thì cho
parents." Then,
nó ra Nó hầu cha hầu mẹ thì đến lúc là
following the master, they said, "Let him go serve his parents. He'll serve for
theo thầy thì thầy bảo là thợ ra hầu thì
three years, then give thanks at the end of the year."
cho Sơn ra hầu Ba năm đầu năm hầu cuối
But they said, "The mother serves first,
năm tạ nhưng họ lại bảo là mẹ hầu trước
then the son serves later." The
thì Con Hầu sau
mother served for three years, then the
mẹ thì lên hầu cũng 3 năm nhưng mà cứ
son served later. The husband
hầu trước thì con lại Hầu sau chồng cũng
believed it and sat there, continuing the blessings for the
tin thì ra ngồi tiếp phúc cho con hầu
son, then the wife, and they threw money
tiếp cho vợ hầu rồi là đủ mọi đem tiền
around and did all sorts of rituals.
tung vãi rồi là hết mọi hình thức trong
Meanwhile, the boy didn't change a single bit until he...  After finishing her
khi đó cháu không chuyển một tí nào đến
studies, she just kept muttering to herself, her eyes staring at people, then laughing. She still went to school as usual, but my nephew, Tâm Chính, is different. He changes his personality very quickly. The family doesn't know what to do. When he finished school and graduated
khi họ Cháu học xong ra trường thì đỗ
with an average grade, they tried to get him a job, but he refused. He
bằng trung bình khá cho cháu đi làm cháu
wandered around, and for
không đi cháu cũng lang thang về nhà thì
10 days, my family was in a
10 ngày thì gia đình tôi là trong một
state of chaos, father and son fighting all 10 days.
cái tình trạng là bố con đánh nhau cả 10
I
luôn đánh nhau tùm lum luôn tức là tôi
thought, "This family is ruined.
bảo Quả này thì nhà này tan nát rồi khả
I might as well just die to end it all.
năng tôi phải chết mẹ đi cho nó xong
Living like this, I can't
cứ sống như thế vậy thì tôi đêm không
sleep at night or eat during the day. If this continues,
ngủ ngày không ăn cứ diễn ra như vậy thì
I can't live with
tôi cũng không thể sống nổi với cái gia
this family anymore. If I die, what will happen to
đình này nếu mà tôi chết thì bây giờ cái
Sơn? What will I do?
thằng Sơn nhà này là làm sao đây biết
He's suddenly become so rude, he's even trying to
làm sao bây giờ tự nhiên là nó nó nó hỗn
kill his parents. My neighbor
nó giết móc bố mẹ chị bên cạnh hàng xóm
told me to come home." So, I suggested taking
chị bảo về chứ thôi Vậy thì cô thử cho
Sơn to the
cái thằng Sơn nó ra bệnh viện tâm thần
Ninh Bình Psychiatric Hospital to see if he has a mental illness. I asked if he was okay, and when I took
Ninh Bình xem hay là nó bị thần kinh
him to the
khám trên có phải không cho cháu lên
Ninh Bình hospital, they said
bệnh viện Ninh Bình thì khám thì nó bảo
to take a urine test, three times, and then another.  My
là ra thử nước tiểu thử ba với lần nước
nephew isn't addicted to
tiểu cháu không bị bị nghiện cái thuốc
any drugs. Then they asked if the family wanted to
gì cả Thế nó bảo vậy thì gia đình có cho
admit him to the
cháu nhập viện không
hospital, and they said yes, he could be admitted
thì họ bảo cho nhập viện thì nhập viện
to Ninh Binh Hospital for 20 days, but they
ở bệnh viện Ninh Bình được 20 ngày nó
didn't transfer him. Then Son asked, "
cũng chẳng chuyển Thế thằng Sơn bảo làm
How can we take him to a psychiatric hospital? It's like you're
sao mà cho ti vào bệnh viện tâm thần Tự
ruining my life!"
nhiên bà đi Bà bà làm hại đời tôi
He said, "It's ruining my life."
thế là nó bảo tin là làm hại đời nó
When Son got home, the hospital
lúc cho Sơn về đến nhà thì bệnh viện họ
still gave him medication to take home. He
vẫn các bạn cấp thuốc cho về nhà uống
took the medication for two
thời gian cháu về Sơn về nhà uống hai
months, his hands and feet shaking, his face swollen, his mouth slurred, his
tháng trời chân tay run phù nề mặt thì
tongue
ngấy mồm thì ngọng không nói được lưỡi
curled, his eyes blurry, he couldn't see anything. His younger brother
cong lại mắt thì mờ không nhìn thấy gì
kept looking at the three types of medicine and said, "
Thằng em nó cứ xem ba loại thuốc nó bảo
Mom, this condition is so bad, throw it all away, don't give
mẹ ơi tình trạng này vứt hết không cho
him this medicine." He threw away all the
uống cái thuốc này nó vứt hết bấy nhiêu
bottles of medicine. Son couldn't sleep. Because he couldn't
lọ thuốc đi thì thằng Sơn là không ngủ
sleep, the two of
được thời gian không ngủ được thì hai vợ
us discussed it and said, "Maybe we should get some traditional
chồng lại bàn nhau bảo là hay là đi cắt
Chinese medicine to help him sleep at night." But he could
thuốc bắc cho nó mát để nó ngủ đêm nó
n't sleep, he stayed awake all night. We stayed awake for
không ngủ vậy nó suốt đêm nó thức Mẹ
half a month like
thức con thức ròng rã Nửa tháng rồi như
this, both mother and son suffering. So we took
thế này mẹ cũng khổ con khổ vậy là lại
traditional Chinese medicine for
dẫn đi cắt thuốc nam thuốc bắc về cho
him to drink, but he didn't seem to get any better.  He
cháu uống cháu uống không thấy đỡ mà nó
kept muttering nonsense, going off looking for a way to
cứ mồm nó Nham nhảm nó vô đi tìm đường
die, and his family was so worried. That day,
nó chết thì gia đình lo quá chứ hôm đấy
he didn't eat, he wandered around until his
thì nó không ăn cơm nó đi lang thang đến
parents went looking for him and couldn't find him. The father
lúc bố mẹ đi tìm không thấy con đâu bố
cried, the son cried, the mother cried, and they still couldn't find him.
khóc Con khóc mẹ khóc mà cũng không thấy
Then he went
đâu cả thời mấy con cô nữa rồi nó lại
up to the banyan tree at the Upper Temple, the temple at the
lên cái cây đa đa ở trên đền Thượng trên
beginning of the village, and sat there. Later,
cái đền đầu làng ấy nó ngồi về sau về
his younger brother said, "Mom, the
thằng em nó mới bảo là mẹ ơi
youngest one beat up the older brother! He said, 'Mom, Mom,
Thằng út nó đánh thằng anh đấy Nó bảo mẹ
Mom, let me open the internet so you can see
ơi mẹ mẹ ơi đưa con mở mạng cho mẹ xem
the Venerable Master Chuc Thai Minh at Ba Vang Temple. He gives such great
cái Thầy chúc Thái Minh ở chùa Ba Vàng
Dharma lectures, Mom!' But
thầy thầy giảng pháp hay lắm mẹ ạ Mà nhà
we didn't know where Ba Vang Temple was, and
ta thì chưa biết chùa Ba Vàng ở đâu mà
Mom went everywhere, praying at different places,
suốt ngày mẹ Đi hết mọi nơi mẹ lễ chỗ nọ
but how come she didn't know where Ba Vang Temple was? The Dharma lectures were
chỗ kia mà sao chùa Ba Vàng Giảng pháp
so good, Mom!
hay vậy mà mẹ không không biết bảo đâu
Where is Ba Vang Temple?" So I opened it for
Chùa Ba Vàng ở đâu vậy thì mình mở cho
her to listen. After listening, she asked to join
mẹ nghe thế là mở nghe xong là xin vào
the Dharma center. She invited the monks from
đạo tràng đạo tràng Thỉnh được Chư tăng
Ba Vang Temple to come and pay her respects to the Buddha. On the
chùa Ba Vàng về cũng có duyên với Phật
3rd of
Pháp về tôn được lô hương mùng 3 tháng
October, she established a Dharma center and held a ceremony.
10 lập Đạo tràng khai đàn thì khai đàn
After the ceremony, she practiced according to the
xong thì là tu tập theo
teachings of the nun and the sister who taught her.  So,
của sự chỉ dạy của cô và chị dạy của đạo
Uncle Thanh, we're just dedicating the merit. We
tràng bác Thanh Vậy là cũng cứ hồi hướng
see that the child is getting better and
Vậy thì là thấy cháu càng ngày cháu càng
better at controlling things. It's only been
điều khiển tốt mới được có
220 days, and we're already seeing such positive results. We're so happy! We're
220 ngày thì đã thấy tốt đẹp thế là mừng
going to brag to the community and fellow
quá với lại đi khoe với đạo tràng mới
practitioners. They ask, "
các đạo hữu các đạo hữu hỏi vậy thỉnh
How's the image of Sister Hang?" Oh my goodness, it's
hình trơn chị Hằng thế nào Ôi dồi ôi
wonderful! The father and son aren't fighting
tuyệt vời rồi bố con nó không đánh nhau
anymore, and I can sleep peacefully, eat
nữa rồi mà tôi được ngủ yên rồi mà ăn
well, and sleep soundly. From that day until now, the child has been well-behaved, hardworking, doesn't
ngon ngủ yên rồi Vậy là từ hôm đến giờ
argue with his father, doesn't beat him, doesn't go out
chửi nhau bố không đánh đập không đi
partying, doesn't run away from home, and isn't doing anything wrong
chơi bời không bỏ nhà đi không làm sao
anymore. He's even getting more handsome every day. He's only just finished
nữa mà càng ngày lại càng đẹp trai hiện
the 49 days of practice, and
giờ là mới tu được có hết cái 49 với lại
tomorrow will be the 19th day
được Hà đến ngày mai mới là được 19 ngày
of the Trung practice. The family is
của cái quyền Trung thì coi như gia đình
now peaceful. My mother-in-law listens to
Bây giờ là êm ấm mẹ chồng thì ngồi nghe
Dharma teachings all day. I go to
pháp suốt ngày Sơn là tôi nào cũng lên
repentance every day.
sám hối
The child still goes to work as his father used to.
cháu vẫn đi làm theo bố mình thường ở
Before, he didn't work, but now he does it
nhà mà trước là không làm giờ cháu làm
normally without needing to be told. He does
bình thường mà không cần phải sai bảo
the work without needing to be told.
không cần thì sai bảo nhìn cái việc là
Honestly, with
làm thì nói thật với lại
the head teacher and the fellow practitioners, the
cô chủ nhiệm và ví dụ các đạo hữu là đến
family is very happy at this point.
giờ này thì gia đình là rất là phấn khởi
When I went with everyone,
mà đi cùng với mọi người là thấy người
people said they didn't know what was wrong with Son. He's so well-behaved
ta bảo không biết làm sao thằng Sơn Dạo
lately, and he looks so quick and agile, not like he used to be. If my family hadn't had the opportunity to learn about Buddhism, by now, my mother would probably be dead, and I would be dead too.
giờ này chắc là mẹ mà chết rồi con chết
The story of my family is
rồi câu chuyện của gia đình nhà tôi thì
long, but I would like to express my gratitude to the
nếu mà nói thì còn dài nữa Nhưng thôi
Three Jewels, to my
xin con xin tri ân Tam Bảo và xin tri ân
teacher Truc Thai Minh, to the
sư phụ thầy Trúc Thái Minh và xin tri ân
great monks of Ba Vang Pagoda, to
đại Chư tăng chùa Ba Vàng rồi con xin
Ms. Pham Thi Yen, the head of the Golden Chrysanthemum
tri ân cô chủ nhiệm Phạm Thị Yến câu lạc
Club practicing the Six Harmonies, and to
bộ Cúc Vàng tập tu Lục Hòa và xin tri ân
all the fellow practitioners in the Golden Chrysanthemum Club.
tất cả các đạo hữu trong câu lạc bộ cúc
Now, my family is happy and joyful, and my
vàng đến giờ này là gia đình hạnh phúc
child is well-behaved.
vui vẻ con ngoan
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
Dear fellow practitioners, we have
Kính thưa các quý đạo hữu chúng ta đã
heard a story from Ms. Hang's family. From
nghe một câu chuyện của nhà chị Hằng từ
a young age, her child was very good at studying and
bé cháu học rất là giỏi và cháu đi học
even went to Hoa University to work as a tutor. After
đại học Hoa còn được làm gia sư thì sau
half a year of studying, the child
đi học được nửa năm mà cháu đã
experienced this, and after the family performed a
bị như vậy và sau khi mà gia đình khai
ritual for over 30 days, the child
đàn Sau hơn 30 ngày là cháu đã chuyển
transformed. Through Ms. Hang's story,
hóa thì qua câu chuyện của chị thì chúng
we see that practicing Buddhism is about
ta thấy rằng tu tập Phật Pháp là chuyển
transformation if one perseveres.  With diligent practice, if
hóa nếu như nỗ lực tu tập thì nếu như
the karmic illness is mild, it will change quickly. With
bệnh nghiệp nhẹ thì sẽ chuyển nhanh với
diligent practice, it will change quickly.
nỗ lực tu tập thì sẽ chuyển nhanh nhà
Your niece, Hang, is 15 years old, is
chị là cháu Hằng 15 rồi đấy chứ có phải
n't she? Yes,
ít đâu phải không chị Vâng 10 năm trời
she suffered like that for 10 years, but with diligent practice
cháu nó bị như thế mà với nỗ lực tu tập
and deep faith, the family
với lòng tin sâu thì có kết quả gia đình
has achieved a change in karma. Congratulations to
đã được chuyển nghiệp thôi Chúc mừng gia
your family! This is also an
đình chị và qua đây cũng là một cái
opportunity for us Buddhists to strive harder,
duyên để cho Phật tử chúng ta tinh tấn
because all that
vì tất cả
listening is not as good as seeing, right?
chăm nghe không bằng một thấy phải không
Just listening without seeing the
ạ Cứ nghe nhưng mà không thấy được sự
truth doesn't mean you believe it. Nothing is transmitted as
thật thì mình không tin là truyền tất cả
truly as experiencing the change of
nghiệm một cách chân thật cái sự chuyển
karma firsthand. Your family's genuine experience of karmic transformation
nghiệp thì gia đình chị trải nghiệm chân
through practice will
thật cái sự tu tập Chuyển Nghiệp thì
surely give you unwavering faith,
chắc chắn là sẽ có lòng tin bất đối
and that faith will help
chuyển và từ cái lòng tin đó sẽ giúp cho
you
mình trong cả một cái cuộc đời này mình
overcome many difficulties throughout your life. I
sẽ tháo gỡ được rất nhiều những khó khăn
also wish the Dharma center
thầy cũng chúc cho đạo tràng làm luôn
continued diligence and development, and
luôn tinh tấn phát triển chứ gia đình
your family happiness. Namo Buddha
chị được hạnh phúc Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư
Shakyamuni. Through this story of Karmic Transformation, I, on behalf of the Dharma center,
Thích Ca Mâu Ni qua câu chuyện được đạo
would like to express my gratitude to the
Nghiệp ngày hôm nay thì xin đại diện cho
Dharma center for participating in today's discussion.  On behalf of the
đạo tràng xin đại diện cho gia đình Đạo
Chuc Son Buddhist community, we respectfully offer our gratitude to the merits of the Three Jewels, the
tràng Chúc Sơn xin được thành kính trên
merits of our
công đức ta chỉ có tam bảo ạ công đức
Master and the monks of Ba Vang Pagoda,
trên sư phụ cùng Chư tăng chùa Ba Vàng
and the merits we receive from the guidance
và công đức mình ấn vào hướng dẫn tu tập
of our club's leader. Because of
của cô chủ nhiệm câu lạc bộ vì những cái
these merits, our community has been able to
công đức ấy cho nên đạo tràng ngày hôm
witness this story of karmic transformation today. We
nay mới được có cái câu chuyện chuyển
also
nghiệp như thế này ạ và đạo tràng cũng
have many more stories of karmic transformation,
đang có rất nhiều những câu chuyện đang
and we respectfully dedicate our gratitude to the club's leader. We also ask for the merits
chuyên công đức cô ạ Và xin Tùy công đức
of all fellow practitioners.
của các đạo hữu
[Music]
[âm nhạc]